<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs coming opened in a sermon before the honourable house of commons in Margaret's Westminster, May 17, 1648 being the day appointed for Thanksgiving for the great Victory in Wales / by William Bridge ...</title>
            <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77362</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E471_3</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50805854</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50805854</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77362)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E471[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs coming opened in a sermon before the honourable house of commons in Margaret's Westminster, May 17, 1648 being the day appointed for Thanksgiving for the great Victory in Wales / by William Bridge ...</title>
                  <author>Bridge, William, 1600?-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Peter Cole ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
                  <note>With: The vvorks of William Bridge, sometime fellow of Emmanuel Colledge in Cambridge, now preacher of the Word of God at Yarmouth. The third volumn. [sic] London : Printed by Peter Cole, at the sign of the Printing-Press in Cornhil, near the Royal Exchange, 1649 -- The saints hiding-place in the time of Gods anger. / By William Bridge ... London, : Printed for Peter Cole, and are to be sold at the sign of the Printing-Presse in Cornhill neer the Royall Exchange., 1647.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Second Advent --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſts coming Opened in a SERMON Before the HONOURABLE HOUSE OF Commons IN <hi>MARGARETS WESTMINSTER:</hi> MAY 17. 1648.</p>
            <p>Being the day appointed for Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving for the great Victory in WALES.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM BRIDGE, Preacher of the Word of God at <hi>Yarmouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Peter Cole</hi> at the Signe of the Printing-Preſſe in Cornhill at the Royall Exchange. 1648.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:162407:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:162407:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:162407:3"/>
            <head>To the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS In PARLIAMENT Aſſembled at <hi>WESTMINSTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand I have preſented theſe notes to your view, ſomewhat concerning the Kingdome and coming of Chriſt: an Argument as unwelcome to ſome, as welcome to others: Kings, Princes, and Rulers ſometimes ſtartle at it, but they need not; for Chriſt meanes them no hurt:
<note place="margin">Quicquid Chriſto datur, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> if they will throw down their Crowns at his feet, he will ſet their Crowns on their heads and his own too.
<note place="margin">Timuiſti perdere terram, &amp;</note> The Jewes feared and refuſed to
<pb facs="tcp:162407:4"/>receive Chriſt and his Kingdome,
<note place="margin">Perdidiſti Deum; ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muiſti ne tollerent gentem, &amp; ſuſtule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Deum; quia te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſti, tenen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do malè a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſti; &amp; ſine terrâ remanſiſti, &amp; ſine Deo. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> in <hi>Joan.</hi> 11.48. Tract.</note> leaſt they ſhould loſe their owne King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and thereby they loſt both their God and their Kingdome, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> obſerves. But who ever loſt his Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter by ſubmitting unto Chriſts Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter? I may ſay truly, <hi>Poteſtas Chriſti</hi> is rather <hi>Cumulativa</hi> then <hi>Privativa.</hi> In helping Chriſt to his Throne, you ſhall helpe your ſelves to your honours and greatneſſe.
<note place="margin">A liquis dicitur ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o adjuvari duplicitèr, vel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem novae vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis; ſic infirmi eſt; ſic Deo non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petir; vel per execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem prioris, in quantum aliquis per alium exequitur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uam or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſic Deus per nos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>djuva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. <hi>Thom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>in.</hi>
               </note> I will not ſay that Chriſt hath need of you, he hath no need of us: But if that of the Schooles be true, <hi>viz.</hi> that one is help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by another, either by addition of new ſtrength and vertue, or by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of what was formerly given, then Jeſus Chriſt may in ſome ſenſe (and that according to Scripture Phraſe, <hi>Judges.</hi> 5.23.) be ſaid to be helped by you. Great confedracies will
<pb facs="tcp:162407:4"/>be raiſed againſt him when he comes to his Kingdome. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.1, 2. But God who ſits in Heaven, laughs at thoſe combinations. v. 4. and in ſpite of them will ſet his King upon his holy hill of <hi>Zion.</hi> v. 6. And to him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh will I give to fit downe with me in my Throne ſayeth our Saviour, even as I have overcome and ſit with my Father in his Throne. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. Wherefore moſt Honourable, be not overcome with evill, be not overcome with difficulties, with oppoſitions or combinations of men; but overcome evill with good, and do what in you lies to bring this bleſſed King Jeſus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Thron and Inheritance, that as al the earth in due time ſhall ſo <hi>England</hi> in ſpeciall manner may become the Kingdom of our Lord Chriſt, and we may all ſay, the Lord God omnipotent reigneth amongſt us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:162407:5"/>
            <p>I could not long deliberate in ſo ſhort a time what part of Gods Word I ſhould preach to you, but knowing the trouble of theſe times, and that the more you ſpend your thoughts on Chriſts coming and Kingdome, the more your hearts will be upheld in the times of your troubles; I choſe rather to preach on this Argument, which I here now preſent, &amp; beſeech the Lord to bleſſe it to you, and you to this Kingdome; onely be ſtrong, and be of good courage; feare not, neither be diſmayed; and the Lord your God will be with you as he hath beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, which ſhall be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant in the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>WILL. BRIDGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162407:5"/>
            <head>CHRISTS COMING Is At OUR MIDNIGHT</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 25. verſ. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And at midnight there was a cry made, Behold, the Bridegroome cometh.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this parable, ye have the ſtate and poſture of the Church a little before, and at the coming of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Then ſhall the Kingdome of heaven be likened unto ten Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins.</hi> verſe 1. Sometimes the Doctrine and grace of the Goſpell, is called the Kingdome of heaven: <hi>The Kingdome of heaven is like to a graine of muſtard-ſeed,</hi> &amp;c. This cannot be meant here; becauſe in the Goſpel there are not ten Virgins. Sometimes the ſtate of glory above is called the Kingdome of heaven: That is not meant here, becauſe there are no fooliſh Virgins. Sometimes the Church of Chriſt under the New Teſtament, is called the Kingdome of heaven; for there God appears, manifeſts himſelfe, and it is heaven on earth: and this is that which is here called the Kingdome of heaven. Which King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is deſcribed by the Governour, King and Head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And by the ſubjects of that Kingdome. The Subjects are deſcribed by their Agreement and Diſagreement. Firſt, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:162407:6"/>agree in this, that they are all Virgins; though ſome fooliſh, yet Virgins, not defiled with men, or the pollutions of the world: 'tis poſſible a fooliſh, and unſound heart may go thus farre in Religion, to be free from the pollutions of the world, yea, through the knowledge of Chriſt, ſayes the Apoſtle <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Secondly, they agree in this, that they have all their Lampes, good and bad, wiſe and fooliſh under Ordinances, which are the Lampes, whereby the golden oyle of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary is emptied into our hearts. Thirdly, they agree in this, that they are all expectants, wiſe and fooliſh wait the bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes comming: they all thinke to receive good, and have a good day by the comming of Jeſus Chriſt: this is farre, yet thus farre may a fooliſh Virgin go. Fourthly, they all agree in this that they had oyle in their lampes: indeed, verſe the 3. it is ſaid,
<note place="margin">Ad nihilu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> valet quod non valet ad finem ſuum.</note> 
               <hi>that the fooliſh Virgins took no oyle with them;</hi> but verſe the 8 they ſay, <hi>Our lampes are gone out:</hi> So that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e they had once, but they had not enough, and ſo none; parts and gifts, and common graces a man may have, not only his lampe but ſome oyle in it for a time, yet be a fooliſh Virgin. Fifthly, they agree in this, that they keep Company, have Communion and fellowſhip together in the Church; yea, ſo farre that the fooliſh are not knowne till Chriſts comming: ſo ſmoothly may a fooliſh Virgin carry it, yet remain fooliſh. Sixthly, They all agree in this alſo; that they hold out their profeſſion, with lamps, and waiting till the bridegroom comes. So that poſſibly, a man may be a Profeſſor of the Goſpel, and beare up his Profeſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the beſt, even to the laſt, yet be unfound at heart, and a fooliſh Virgin. Thus farre they agree.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, though theſe Virgins agree in many things, yet they diſagree in the point of wiſedome: for the wiſe got ſo much oyle as did ſerve till the laſt; the fooliſh not ſo: there was <hi>defectus olei,</hi> verſe 8.</p>
            <p>Secondly you have here the deſcription of the King, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour and Head of this Kingdome, who is deſcribed from and by the manner of his coming. Firſt, he comes as a Bridegroom. Secondly, he comes apparently. Not as in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162407:6"/>the dayes of his fleſh when he came more hiddenly; <hi>behold a great cry, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, he comes ſuddenly, unexpectedly, in the moſt darke time, he comes at midnight.</p>
            <p>Now Chriſts coming is either <hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>inviſible, John</hi> 14.18. <hi>I will not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you,</hi> Or <hi>viſible:</hi> and that either at the day of judgement: or elſe at the calling and converſion of the Jewes, when he will appeare in the clouds, and come to ſet up his Kingdome in this world, in a more glorious manner then ever. So <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Behold, he cometh with cloudes, and every eye ſhall ſee him, and they alſo which pierced him,</hi> that is the Jewes, <hi>and all kindreds of the earth ſhall waile becauſe of him, even ſo, Amen.</hi> Which relates unto the 12. Chapter of <hi>Zachariah,</hi> verſe the 10, 11, 12, 13, 14. <hi>I will pour upon the houſe of</hi> David, <hi>and upon the inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>the Spirit of grace and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; and they ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him as one mourneth for his only ſon, &amp;c. In that day there ſhall be a great mourning in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and the land ſhall mourn, every family apart; the family of the houſe of</hi> David apart, <hi>and their wives apart; the family of the houſe of</hi> Nathan <hi>apart, and their wives apart; the family of the houſe of</hi> Levi <hi>apart, and their wives apart, &amp;c.</hi> Which cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the day of judgement, becauſe then the families of <hi>David, Nathan, Shimei, Levi,</hi> ſhall not mourne apart, and their wives apart. Of this coming of Chriſt to ſet up his Kingdome, I rather take this parable to be underſtood, and not of his coming at the day of judgement; for in the 24. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> the Diſciples did propound three queſtions to our Saviour Chriſt, verſe the 3. <hi>Tell us, when ſhall theſe things be?</hi> that is the deſtruction of the Temple; <hi>and what ſhall be the ſigne of thy coming, and of the end of the world?</hi> To the laſt he doth anſwer firſt (as is uſuall in Scripture,) negatively, verſe the 6. <hi>Ye ſhall heare of warres and rumours of warres, but the end is not yet.</hi> Affirmatively verſe the 14. <hi>And this Goſpel of the Kingdome, ſhall be preached in all the world for a witneſſe to all Nations, and then ſhall the end come.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:162407:7"/>To the firſt queſtion he doth anſwer in the ſecond place, verſe the 15, and 16. And to the ſecond he doth anſwer in the third and laſt place, becauſe he intended to ſpeake moſt to that, and ſo proceeds to ſpeake of his coming and the ſignes thereof, in the after part of the 24. Chapter, and verſe the 37, 39, 40, 44, 46, 50. and ſo he goes on in this beginning of the 25. <hi>Then ſhall the Kingdome of Heaven be like unto ten virgins.</hi> In which parable ſtill he ſpeakes of his coming as before, for verſe 13. he concludes this parable thus, <hi>Watch ye therefore, for ye know not the houre wherein the Son of man cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, Chriſt comes not as a Bridegroome, but as a Judge at the day of judgement. And if ye look into the 19, 21, 22 chapters of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> where mention is made of the glory of Chriſts kingdome in the latter times, ye find, that the converting Jew, who there ſings the Hebrew ſong <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luja,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled, the Bride, the Lambes wife, ſaying, <hi>Come Lord Jeſus.</hi> And at the eighteen and nineteene verſes of the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter, mention is made of a great battell: But there is no fighting, nor battelling at the day of judgement; That is no time for feaſting, nor ſuppers neither; but at weddings and marriages there were, and are great ſuppers, which we reade ſhall be at this time, verſe 17. And as the wiſe enter, ſo the fooliſh, and thoſe that tell, and make lies are ſhut out. Finding therefore all theſe things at that coming of Chriſt, thus to ſuit with this parable, I rather incline to thinke, that it cannot be underſtood of the day of judgement, but of that time when Chriſt will appeare at the Jewes converſion, to ſet up his kingdome on earth, in that glorious, and bleſſed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner which all the Prophets beare witneſſe unto.</p>
            <p>And becauſe all the Victories, and deliverances that Chriſt worketh for the churches in the meane time, are ſo many ſteps unto this kingdome, and coming of his: therefore in Scripture phraſe, ſometimes, they are called his coming. <hi>Matthew</hi> 17. His transfiguration was called his coming in his Kingdome; for Chapter 16.28. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>There be ſome ſtanding here, which ſhall not taſte of death till they ſee the ſon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:162407:7"/>of man coming in his Kingdome.</hi> And then verſe 1. Chapter 17. it is ſaid, <hi>And after ſix dayes, Jeſus taketh</hi> Peter, James <hi>and</hi> John <hi>his brother, and bringeth them up into an high mountaine apart, and was transfigured before them.</hi> In three Goſpels, this hiſtory of the transfiguration is linked unto that ſpeech, <hi>There are ſome ſtanding here, which ſhall not taſte of death till they ſee the ſon of man coming in his Kingdome,</hi> with thoſe words, <hi>And after ſix dayes Jeſus tooke</hi> Peter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Lord and Saviour Chriſt was then come when he ſpake thoſe words; but he was to come in a more glorious way and manner to ſet up his Kingdome, and his transfiguration being a taſte of that glory and coming, it is here called his coming in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. So all theſe great deliverances and victories which Chriſt worketh for his Church, being ſo many taſts, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of his coming in his Kingdome, they may be called his coming too; ſurely, they are as ſo many ſteps that he takes in the way of his coming to his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>But ſayes the text, He comes at midnight; That is, in a time when he is leaſt expected, ſuddenly, and when we are moſt in the dark. And ſo the Obſervation is this.</p>
            <p>Chriſt comes at midnight: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Though his coming be moſt expected, yet he will come in a time when he is leaſt expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; when he comes as a Bridegroome, he comes at midnight, in a time when he is leaſt expected, in the darkeſt time; Chriſt comes at midnight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold</hi> (ſayes Chriſt) <hi>I come as a thief;</hi> theeves come in the darkeſt time, a time when they are leaſt expected; ſo will Chriſts coming be.</p>
            <p>For the opening and clearing of which truth, I ſhall labour to ſhew,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That our Lord and Saviour Chriſt will come againe. Secondly, That he will come at midnight. Thirdly, Give you ſome account why he chooſes rather thus to come at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, then otherwiſe. And then draw down this by way of Application to our preſent occaſion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Our Lord and Saviour Chriſt will come againe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Take his coming for, his <hi>Spirituall</hi> coming; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162407:8"/>though now abſent from your ſoule, yet he will come againe. <hi>John</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man love me, my father will love him, and we will come unto him and make our abode with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Take his coming for his <hi>Perſonall,</hi> viſible co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming at the day of judgement, ſo he will come again. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. Chap. 7, 8, 9, 10. verſes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Take his coming for his <hi>appearing in the cloudes,</hi> when he will come to ſet up his Kingdome, ſo he will come again before that great day; for if ye look into the Scripture, ye ſhall find that his coming and his Kingdome are knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, do ſynchronize <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14.</p>
            <p>So in many Scriptures ye ſhall find his coming, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome do go together. Now if ye look into the 11. of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, we ſhall find it ſpoken of times yet to come; <hi>The Kingdomes of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord, and his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever and ever:</hi> verſ. the 15. <hi>And we give thee thanks, O Lord, God Almighty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy great power, and haſt reigned,</hi> verſe 17. which cannot be underſtood of the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for then the Nations are not angry, then the Temple-doore is not opened, as is here ſaid verſe 18, and 19.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſtaken here; for I do not thinke that Chriſt ſhall come and raigne, continue raigning upon earth a thouſand years, I do not ſee how the Saints can ſpare him out of heaven ſo long. Neither do I thinke that this his coming is onely to be underſtood of a ſpirituall coming into the ſouls of his, ſo filling their ſoules with his ſpirit, that they ſhall have need of Ordinances no more; for in thoſe glorious times, though there ſhall be no Temple, that is, a Jewiſh Temple, yet the Temple doore, that is, the Goſpel Temple, ſhall be opened. And in <hi>Zachariah</hi> the laſt, which is plainly ſpoken of the glory of the latter times yet to come, it is ſaid expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three times in that Chapter, that men ſhall go up to keep the feaſt of Tabernacles, an alluſion to the Jewiſh Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. But why not the feaſt of Paſſcover and Pentecoſt, onely the feaſt of Tabernacles? many reaſons may be given,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:162407:8"/>but I think one is; Becauſe the feaſt of Tabernables had been more neglected then other feaſts; for upon the coming out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the 8. of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 'tis ſaid, they had not kept that feaſt from the time of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun</hi> to that day, which was almoſt a thouſand yeares. Now the Holy Ghoſt ſeeing what degenerations there would be in our latter times, and loſings, and neglectings of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, he ſaith here, that then they ſhall keep the feaſt of Tabernacles: that is, in the expreſſion of the Jews, obſerve thoſe Ordinances eſpecially, which had been moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and forgotten: But I keepe to the words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſhall come in the cloudes again, when the poor Jewes ſhall ſee him, and thoſe which are called Forſaken,
<note place="margin">Reade ch. 13 of the 2. of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> which though it be Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha and the loweſt of Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, being written in Latin, yet of great antiquity, cited by <hi>Cyprian, Jerome, Auſtin, Cle mens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> and divers others.</note> ſhall be called Beloved the Kings bride, when the fulneſſe of the Gentiles ſhall be come in, when Chriſt himſelf ſhall ſet up his Kingdome in the world, his <hi>Regnum potentiae,</hi> not <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiae:</hi> when he ſhall rule from ſea to ſea, when he ſhall come not riding upon an aſſes colt, but in the cloudes, with thouſands of Angels miniſtring unto him. When fooliſh virgins ſhall be ſhut out from his glory, and the wiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor taken in. And in the meane while, though our Lord and Saviour Chriſt ſeeme to forſake the Churches for the preſent, yet he will come againe unto them with delivering and conquering mercy: <hi>Behold, I come quickly, hold faſt that which thou haſt.</hi> Revel. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But how may it appeare that Chriſt will come at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw</hi> I ſhall give you a taſte of it in all his comings, becauſe there is the ſame Spirit in one as in another.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For his ſpirituall coming, when Chriſt comes firſt with his <hi>Converting</hi> grace, and cauſes his <hi>Converting</hi> mercy to paſſe upon any ſoule, then he doth come at midnight, <hi>Job.</hi> 33. <hi>God ſpeaketh once, yea twice, yet man perceives it not; in a dreame, in a viſion of the night, when deepe ſleep falleth upon men, in ſlumbrings upon the bed, Then he openeth the eares of men, and ſealeth their inſtruction,</hi> verſe 14, 15, 16. When
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:162407:9"/>a man is faſt aſleepe in his ſins, little thinkes of any good, unleſſe it be to oppoſe it, then Chriſt comes and ſeales on ſome inſtruction upon his ſoule. Thus he doth come at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> When Chriſt comes with his <hi>Comforting</hi> mercy, and cauſes his comforting grace to paſſe upon a mans heart; then he doth come at midnight, in an houre and time when he doth leaſt expect him. <hi>I ſought him</hi> (ſayes the Spouſe,) <hi>but I found him not. I ſought him on my bed,</hi> in private, <hi>and found him not. I ſought him in the ſtreets,</hi> in the publique Ordinances, but I found him not. <hi>It was but a little that I paſſed from the watchmen, but I found him whom my Soule lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</hi> Then, and there ſhe finds him, where ſhe look't not for him, and did not expect him. Pſalme 42. verſe 6, 7, 8. <hi>O my God</hi> (ſayes <hi>David). My Soule is caſt down within me.</hi> Here's trouble, ſorrow, and heavineſſe; <hi>all thy waves are gone over me,</hi> verſe the 17. Here's more. Yet (ſaith he) verſe 8. <hi>The Lord will command his loving kindneſſe in the day time, and in the night his ſongs ſhall be with me.</hi> It is Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary title, <hi>The Lord our maker, who giveth ſongs in the night,</hi> Job. 35. We reade of Maſter <hi>Robert Glover,</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by Maſter <hi>Fox,</hi> in the booke of Martyrs, That though he were a man very gracious and holy, faithfully bearing witneſſe to the truth; yet it pleaſed God to withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and preſence from him, in ſo much that he was greatly diſtreſſed while he was in priſon; and opening himſelfe to his friend, told him, how God had left and deſerted him; his friend exhorted him ſtill for to waite on God, which he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to do, and the night before his execution, ſpent much of that time in prayer, yet no comfort came, no manifeſtations of the preſence of Chriſt; the next day he was drawn out to the ſtake for to die for the truth, and as he went, he mourned much for the preſence of Chriſt; but when he came in the ſight of the ſtake, it pleaſed God ſo to fill his heart and ſoule with comfort, and the incomes of his love, that he cried out unto his friend, O <hi>Auſtin,</hi> heis come, he is come, he is come. This good man was in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:162407:9"/>darke a great while; but when in the darkeſt time, then Chriſt came. Chriſt comes at midnight, when he doth come with comfort.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> When Chriſt comes with outward delivering mercy to a perſon or people, then he doth come at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night alſo. It is ſaid of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they went out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> at midnight. God had promiſed deliverance a long time before, and they did all expect it; but who would have expected it at ſuch a time as that was? And if we look into that laſt Chapter of <hi>Zachary,</hi> we ſhall find, that the great deliverance of the Churches promiſed, is to be <hi>in one day, which ſhall be known to the Lord, not day nor night, but it ſhall come to paſſe, that at evening time it ſhall be light,</hi> verſe 7. Who would expect light at evening? we all expect darkneſſe at evening time; but at evening, when we looke moſt for darkneſſe, God hath promiſed this great light.</p>
            <p>And for Chriſts coming at the laſt, ye know what he ſayes, <hi>I will come in an houre when ye looke not for me.</hi> And for this great deliverance and victory which the Lord hath now given unto you, was it not at midnight? conſider with your ſelves a little, remember the dayes of your former troubles, and were you ever in a more darke condition? were ye not all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nighted? when were your enemies more high, and lofty? when were your friends more down and dejected? A night, a night, the Lord knowes, a darke night was come upon us. Well, but now Chriſt comes with a ſeaſonable, almoſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous victory and deliverance. And this is Chriſts way and manner; He never comes to his people as a Bridegroome, but ſtill he doth come at midnight, in all his comings ſtill he doth come at midnight.</p>
            <p>Chriſt loves that his people ſhould ſit up for him, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> watch and waite for him. He waiteth to ſhew mercy on them that waite on his mercy. The more a man is reſpected, and beloved in an houſe, the more if he be abroad, thoſe in the houſe will ſit up, and watch for him; he that loves him not, ſayes, I will go to bed, I'le ſtay no longer, let him come when he pleaſes; but he that loves him, ſaith, I'le watch, I'le ſtay, I'le ſit
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:162407:10"/>up for him; yea, though he don't come till midnight.</p>
            <p>And does it argue love, for one man to ſit up and waite for another? and not love in our ſoules to ſit up and watch, and waite for Chriſt? Chriſt loves to ſee our love exerciſed; and therefore ſayes he, though I intend to ſave, and helpe ſuch a perſon, yet I'le ſtay, and ſtay long; I will not helpe him preſently, I'le ſuffer a night, a darke night to come upon him, ſo ſhall I ſee his love in waiting for me.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Chriſt loves to ſhew mercy to his people in ſuch a way, as he may hide pride from men; he would not have his people to be proud of mercies. And upon this account ſayes the text, in the 33. of <hi>Job. He ſeales on inſtruction in the night, that he may hide pride from man.</hi> When a man is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, he tryes things by reaſon, and if reaſon like them, then they do paſſe for currant; if reaſon don't approve them, then they will be rejected: but in a dreame, in a deep ſleep, the mind receives things, not examining them by reaſon. Now in the great things of God, the leſſe hand reaſon hath, and the more Faith,
<note place="margin">Rationes p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aeceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentes augent.</note> the better. Reaſons going before Faith, do diminiſh it; but Reaſons following Faith, ſtrengthen it, ſay the Schooles. Faith ennobles a worke. The more a man uſhers in a buſineſſe with his owne reaſon, the more apt to be proud thereon: but in a dream, in a deep ſleep, there is little of reaſon to be uſed, and therefore in a deep ſleep he comes upon us, that he may hide pride from us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Chriſt loves to come ſo, as he may be moſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to his people; and the leſſe expected, the more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come many times: and when is he leſſe expected then at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night? If a man be in extremity of miſery, and a friend comes to viſit him, then he doth not onely bid him welcome, but admires his love: Oh! Sir, could you find in your heart to come to me now? what! now at midnight? this is love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. Chriſt comes to be admired of all that beleeve, (ſayes the Scripture) and therefore, when his people are in the darke, in a darke night, then he chooſes to come, and then eſpecially; and then a mans heart doth melt with love to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:162407:10"/>Chriſt: Oh! what a gracious Saviour have I, that could find in his heart to find me out with his mercy in this darke condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in this unexpected time! His time is not as our time, as his thoughts are not as ours. Chriſt is the good Samaritan, he will poure wine and oyle into the bleeding wounds of his ſervants, but he will firſt let the Prieſt paſſe by, and the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite paſſe by, and ſuch meanes and helpes paſſe by, which we ordinarily expect comfort from; and when we have none from them, then ſayes he, now is a time for me; but by that time all other helpes are paſſed by, it will be midnight; but though it be midnight (ſayes Chriſt) it is all one to me, for I create light, and my thoughts, and my times, are not as mans are. And though man come with help and ſuccour in the day time, yet I will come at midnight. Oh! <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label> what glorious diſpenſations of love and mercy is here!</p>
            <p>What is the iſſue of this doctrine? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> what if Chriſt do come at midnight?</p>
            <p>This Doctrine lookes wiſhly upon two ſorts of people, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> ſuch as he doth come againſt, and ſuch as he doth come for.</p>
            <p>Some fooliſh virgins there are whom Chriſt comes againſt, and theſe he will come upon at midnight, take them in their beds, when they are faſt aſleepe in their ſin, and are moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure. Ye have heard of the lamentation of <hi>Norwich;</hi> there was a generation of men that roſe up and threatned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the godly Party there; but the Lord ſo ordered things in his providence, that thoſe whom they threatned to deſtroy, were preſerved, and the deſtroyers periſhed; nigh two or three hundred (if relations be right) blown up with powder, or ſpoiled, and three godly families, conſiſting of about twenty perſons, in ſeverall roomes of the houſe that was blowne up, were all preſerved, and not a bone of them broken, whilſt the other flew up into the aire, as ſpectacles of divine anger, as if God ſhould ſpeak from Heaven, theſe are the people whom I would have preſerved, and thoſe are the people, that I would have puniſhed. But ah! poore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed ſoules who periſhed in the thunder of Gods anger,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:162407:11"/>did they ever thinke that Chriſt would have come upon them at ſuch a midnight? Here is a great deliverance and victory that is now before ye: If relations ſpeak true, two thouſand and five hundred, putting to flight eight thouſand of the enemy, fifteene hundred ſlaine, three thouſand taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, and the reſt ſcattered: But ah! poor deceived people who made this inſurrection? did they ever thinke that Chriſt would have come ſo ſuddenly, in ſuch a time, at midnight upon them? Conſider all your warres, and hath not Chriſt come at midnight all along? Chriſt is in the way to his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and every ſtep he takes ſhall be midnight; both unto thoſe he comes for, and thoſe that he comes againſt; but woe to them whom he doth come againſt, it is adreadfull thing to be cutt off ſuddenly, and ſurprized in our ſins. This is a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment threatned on the latter day, Chriſt will come quickly, be quick with men in a way of judgment: as a thief in the night will he come, when poor fooliſh virgins ſhall be faſt aſleep.</p>
            <p>I would h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e therfore exhort and beſeech ye in the Lord, to conſider the grounds ye ſtand upon, the principles ye worke by, the cauſe ye mannage; and I appeale to you, whether do ye not thinke that God is in all theſe warres, that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of battels is only in the hand of God? Some of you, no friends to Parliament, nor the cauſe of God in their hands, have tryed many wayes (as once <hi>Balaam,</hi>) to curſe <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſometimes ye have got upon one hill, and there ye have built an altar, thinking from thence to curſe Gods people; when that would not do, then ye got upon a ſecond; when ye could not do it from thence, then ye got to a third moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: one while ye thought to have done it by the ſtrength of your old skilfull ſoldiery; when that would not do, then ye came home, and ſought to make diviſions among us, and to raiſe jealouſies between brethren; ſeeing that would not do it ſufficiently, you have now gotten to a third mountain, labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtir up the Countreys to make inſurrection, and yet you cannot curſe them from thence. Wherefore now after all, do ye not thinke that God is againſt you? can ye beleeve that God is with you, after all theſe ſucceſſive victories that have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:162407:11"/>fallen againſt you? Have ye not read that Scripture, <hi>The Lord is knowne by the judgement which he executeth, the wicked are ſnared in the workes of their owne hands?</hi> and have ye not been ſnared in the works of your owne hands? have ye not riſen to fall? have not your own doings, been your undoing? and will ye yet go on to plot, conſult, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne? what? will ye never have done? well then, go on, conſult, plot, deviſe, aſſociate, confederate together, try the concluſion, worke to the utmoſt; yet know, that when ye have done all, and as you thinke have the better, and all is your owne, then will Chriſt come upon you at midnight, in an houre and time, when ye do leaſt expect him, and it will be a darker night then ever yet you ſaw; for our Lord and Saviour Chriſt, he doth come as at the laſt, ſo now in theſe his precedaneous comings, ſtill at midnight, he doth come at midnight. Be wiſe now therefore, O ye Princes, Nobles, Rulers, Judges, Gentlemen, and others: Kiſſe the Son, leſt ye periſh in the way, for Chriſt is upon his way unto his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This Doctrine looks wiſhly upon ſuch as Chriſt comes for. Why ſhould any of Gods people deſpaire or be diſcouraged, ſaying, Chriſt is now gone, and will never come againe, he hath hid himſelf, and I ſhall never ſee his face againe; Nay, but he comes at midnight, that is his time, a time wherein he is leaſt expected, a darke time, the darkeſt time, the ſleepieſt time, the coldeſt time, a time when all your candles are out, and your comforts out, when you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee your hand, your working hand, your praying hand, when you ſay all is gone and loſt, and I ſhall never ſee the light againe, comfort again, then doth Chriſt ſay, this is my time, it is now darke, and night, and midnight with my ſervant, now will I go and comfort and deliver him: why ſhould any godly man be diſcouraged, what ever his condition be? ſhall Chriſt come at midnight, and ſhall I be diſcouraged becauſe I am in the darke? O my ſoule, remember this, Chriſt comes at midnight, in all his comings ſtill he doth come at midnight. And that this is Chriſts conſtant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:162407:12"/>courſe with all his people, ſee what is ſaid in the 6. of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>Then ſhall we know if we follow on to know the Lord, his going forth is prepared as the morning, and he ſhall come unto us as the raine, as the latter and former raine unto the earth.</hi> Oh! but I am a poore ignorant creature, don't know or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the mind, and will of God in theſe actions, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of things abroad. Be it ſo, yet (ſayes the Lord) you ſhall know him, if you follow on to know him. Oh! but I am in a ſad and a darke condition, benighted with ſome affliction. Be it ſo, Chriſt will come, and he will come as the morning; as ſure and certain as the morning comes, ſo will Chriſt come; and though it be a darke night, yet you ſay, certainly morning will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; ſo confident may you be of Chriſts coming; for (ſaith the text) he will come as the morning: that is, certainly. Oh! but I ſhall faint in the meane while, he will ſtay long ere he comes. Nay, but he will come in ſeaſon, as the former, and as the latter raine; the former and the latter raine come in their ſeaſons; ſo will Chriſt do, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall your comforts ſhall be all revived and refreſhed; why ſhould then any of Gods people be diſcouraged?</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that the Lord Jeſus do comfortably appear to us in a darke condition, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> when we look not for him, as now he hath done to this Kingdome: what is our duty that doth flow from hence?</p>
            <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> If Jeſus Chriſt hath appeared to you in the darke, and come to you even at midnight; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Duty. </seg>1</label> then truſt in the Lord for ever; and againe I ſay, truſt in the Lord, truſt in the Lord at all times. Here is one night over, but another night will come (I feare) and it may prove a darker night; night and day have their courſes.
<note place="margin">Nec ſuper biendum rebus flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus, nec deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum adverſis.</note> But does Chriſt come at midnight? why then ſhould we not truſt in God at midnight, in the darkeſt time? <hi>At what time I am afraid</hi> (ſayes the Pſalmiſt) <hi>I will truſt in the Lord</hi> Faith moves Chriſt for to come the ſooner: And therefore (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>Looking for, and haſtening the coming of the Lord.</hi> You reade it in the Engliſh,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> haſtening unto; but according to the Greek, the words may better be read thus, looking for, and haſtening
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:162407:12"/>the coming of the Lord. Our very looking for his coming,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Pet. 3.12.</note> doth haſten his coming. Faith mitigates our calamities, and holds the hands of our enemies. I have read in the life of <hi>Tindall,</hi> that he being in the Low-countreyes, heard of a certaine Jugling Conjurer, that could by his conjuring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a diſh of meate from any Princes table in the world, which he did uſe to do, and would ordinarily invite his friends unto dinner: Whereupon Maſter <hi>Tindall</hi> reſolved, that he would go ſee this act, but would ſet himſelfe to beleeve the contrary; which he did; &amp; the company being come together, and the Conjurer indeavouring the ſame, was ſo hindred by the faith of Maſter <hi>Tindall,</hi> that he cried out, and ſaid,
<note place="margin">Fidearma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, diſſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia quaeq, poteſt.</note> I cannot do it, there ſits the man that hinders me, and holds my hands. I ſay, faith will hold the hands of wicked and deviliſh men; ſuch too many we have to deale with in theſe times: Oh! that you would uſe your faith more and more. And have ye not ground enough for it? Chriſt comes at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; why ſhould you not beleeve what ever your condition be, although it be never ſo darke?</p>
            <p>Secondly, If Chriſt come at midnight, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Duty. </seg>2</label> then why ſhould thoſe who are imployed for Chriſt, be ſhaken, or unſetled in his worke and ſervice?</p>
            <p>We many times leave Gods work, and are not conſtant in it becauſe of oppoſition, which doth make us fear: But will Chriſt come and own us, and come in a time when we looke not for him, in the darkeſt time? then why ſhould not men go on with all conſtancy, even in their darkeſt feares? <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> relates a ſtory of <hi>Auſtins</hi> mother, (which alſo <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth mention) who was much troubled for her ſon <hi>Auſtin,</hi> becauſe that for the ſpace of ſeven or nine years, he had been a Manichee; ſhe prayed &amp; continued praying for him; at the laſt in the night, ſhe had as a word from God in anſwer to her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, theſe words, <hi>Qualis tu, talis ille;</hi> As thou, ſo he. Whereupon ſhe was much refreſhed, and told him, ſhe had received a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe from the Lord that he ſhould be converted from his error; but he told her the meaning of the words was contrary, that ſhe ſhould be as he was, that is, converted to his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:162407:13"/>But ſhe did ſo conſtantly abide in her ſence,
<note place="margin">Ad-ò con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r manebat in ſuo ſen ſu, ut <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustinus</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ivit in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ris. <hi>Luth.</hi> in Gen.</note> that, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile tranſivit in ſententiam matris,</hi> he eaſily turned to his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers opinion. And indeed, what more convincing to an adverſary then to ſee one conſtantly abiding by what is good? A Chriſtian, eſpecially a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, ſhould be like to Chriſt, who when he is in a way of mercy, will not be put out of his way by men. <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 27. verſe 4. <hi>Who would ſet the bryars and thornes againſt me in battell? I would go through them, I would burne them together.</hi> At the 2. and 3. verſe, he ſpeakes of his great love, and care to and of his Church: <hi>A vine-yard of red wine, I the Lord do keepe it, I will water it every moment, leaſt any hurt it, I will keep it night and day.</hi> I but in this vine-yard, there may be many briars and thornes, that may ariſe up to afflict Gods people. True, But (ſayes the Lord) who would ſet the briars and thornes againſt me in battell? I would go through them. As if he ſhould ſay, Indeed theſe wicked men are as briars and thornes, rending and tearing my poore people, and as briars and thornes they do conjoyne and twiſt together; but though they do riſe up againſt me in the way of my mercy towards my people, yet they ſhall not put me out of my way, I will even paſſe through them: yea, and though they do riſe, it ſhall be to their owne ruine, they ſhall burne together, I would burne them together, I the Lord would paſſe through them. Now our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, I hope, is in the way of mercy to this poore Kingdome; but certainly, he is upon the way to his own Kingdome; and though wicked men may obſtruct, and hinder us, they ſhall never hinder him, but he will paſſe through them. Oh! therefore, labour more and more to be like to Chriſt, keep on your way; for though it be late ere he come, yet he will certainly come, he comes at midnight.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Duty. </seg>3</label> If Jeſus Chriſt have come unto us even at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night: why ſhould not all of us go forth to meet him with ſome preſent of thankfulneſſe? The more abundant, full, free, and continued any mercy is, the more it doth call for thankfulneſſe. Chriſt hath been in the field for you and fought
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:162407:13"/>your battels for theſe many years; and I muſt needs ſay, that of late our diviſions and ſins have been ſo great, that I feared they would even drive Chriſt out of the field: but now I ſee ſtill he doth own your cauſe, and own your forces, ſtill he doth keepe the field; yea, and goes on marching, as if he were reſolved not to leave the field, till he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered all this Kingdome with his love; and he hath now given you a taſte of his intentions and love in this victory, a ſeaſonable victory, a wonderfull victory, an unexpected victory, a midnight victory; Oh! thou Wonder-working God! ſhall we not now praiſe thy name? We reade of a great ſtraight and darke condition that <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> was in by reaſon of his enemies; but he crying unto the Lord, the Lord heard and delivered him and his people: in ſo much as they kept a day of thankſgiving in the open fields, and they called the name of the place <hi>Berachah,</hi> the valley of bleſſing. 2 Chron. 20.26.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Joſhua's</hi> time the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in a great ſtraight, by reaſon of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> who came upon them when they were weake; but the Lord fought for his people, ſmote their enemies, and they were quite deſtroyed; whereupon <hi>Iſrael</hi> made an Altar, and called it <hi>Jehovah-niſſi,</hi> The Lord my ſhield. In <hi>Samucls</hi> time again, they were in a great diſtreſſe by reaſon of their enemies; but they cried to the Lord, and he delivered them, and deſtroyed all their enemies: then they ſet up a ſtone, and called it, <hi>Eben-ezer,</hi> The ſtone of help, ſaying, <hi>Hitherunto the Lord hath holpen us.</hi> Afterwards againe, they were brought very low into a very darke eſtate, ſould into the hands of their enemies, but the Lord raiſed them up Saviours, <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak,</hi> and delivered them from all their enemies; and then they penned a Pſalme of praiſe, the 5. of <hi>Judges,</hi> wherein they do aſcribe and give the glory of all unto God himſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they make an honourable mention of the inſtruments which God uſed; they did not revile the inſtruments, but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured them; wherein they condemned and curſed thoſe that would not go forth to help the Lord; curſe ye <hi>Meroz:</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:162407:14"/>Wherein they commended the Tribes and Countreyes who came forth and willingly offred themſelves unto the ſervice of the Lord; wherein they prayed againſt the enemies of the Church: And then marke the iſſue (at the laſt verſe) <hi>And the Land had reſt forty yeares.</hi> And ſuch an iſſue, not onely forty yeares, but many times forty yeares reſt, may you have as an iſſue of the praiſes of this day.</p>
            <p>But yet obſerve, ſtill ſome monument of praiſe was erected; ſometimes a ſtone, ſometimes an Altar, alwayes one monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or other of praiſe. And have we no Altar? no ſtone now? no name of God to celebrate now? no preſent of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to bring to our God this day? is there no act of mercy to be ſhowne? none of Chriſts friends to be relieved? ſhall we make no progreſſe? ſhall we ſtand ſtill? doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? as men in a maze? ſhall we make no improvement of this deliverance and victory? why ſhould we not all ſit down under our relations, and ſay, How ſhall I make im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of this mercy? what ſhall I do now for God and Chriſt that I did not before? Is there nothing in your hand? what? No preſent to be given to Chriſt? have we nothing at all? then let us bring the ſence of our own Nothing; for the more humble ye are after victories, the more thankfull for victories. And if ye have no preſent in your hand this day to bring unto God for this victory,
<note place="margin">Imago Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar is red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari, imago Dei redda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Deo. <hi>August.</hi>
               </note> yet bring the victory it ſelfe, and give it to God. Ye give to Ceſar the things that are Ceſars: why? becauſe his image is upon them; and hath not this victory much of the image of God upon it? When <hi>David</hi> was delivered from his enemies, we reade in the 116. Pſalme, that he checks himſelfe for his former un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe, <hi>I ſaid in my haſte, &amp;c.</hi> and gathers up himſelf into God againe;
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In ingenu is. <hi>Ar. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan.</hi> ſic <hi>Tarnov.</hi> in Pſalm. paſſion.</note> 
               <hi>Returne unto thy reſt O my ſoule.</hi> When deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from his enemies, as we reade in the 118. Pſalme, he ſounds a retrate from man, O my ſoule, truſt not in Princes, not in man, nor in the ſons of men, truſt not in Princes. The word in the Hebrew is, Ingenuous men, for Princes ſhould be ingenuous; and if any men are to be truſted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:162407:14"/>to, they are ingenuous men; but being delivered from men, he retreates from men, and ſayes, O my ſoule, truſt not in men, nor in the ſons of men, not in Princes, not in ingenuous men.</p>
            <p>Yea, and in that Pſalme, he cals upon others alſo for to praiſe the Lord; and ſo let us do in his words: <hi>O give thanks unto the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy endures for ever: He ſtilleth the rage of the ſea, and the tumults of the people, for his mercy endures for ever.</hi> Who hath owned your cauſe again, and your forces again, for his mercy endures for ever; who hath remembred you in your low condition, for his mercy endures for ever; and hath viſited us with his love at midnight, for his mercy endures for ever: <hi>O give thanks unto the God of Gods, for his mercy endures for ever. Praiſe the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If Chriſt come at midnight,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Applic.</hi> 2.</note> then me thinkes his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall coming is not farre off. I cannot ſay it is midnight in that reſpect, but ſurely it is very late, it is very darke, and it hath been darke a great while.</p>
            <p>We reade of two ſorts of ſignes, which go before the coming of Jeſus Chriſt: Some that are more remote and tranſient, ſome that are more immediate and juſt at his coming. Thoſe that are more immediate and juſt at his coming, ye reade of in the 24. of <hi>Matth.</hi> verſ. 29, 30. <hi>Immediately after the tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of thoſe dayes ſhall the ſunne be darkened, and the moone ſhall not give her light, and the ſtarres ſhall fall from Heaven, and the powers of the Heavens ſhall be ſhaken, and then ſhall appear the ſigne of the Sonne of man in Heaven; and then ſhall all the tribes of the earth mourne, and they ſhall ſee the Sonne of man coming in the clouds of Heaven with power and great glory.</hi> Theſe are yet to come. But thoſe that are more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, all ſeeme to be paſt already. Before the coming of Chriſt (ſayes the Apoſtle) the man of ſin ſhall be revealed; that is paſt. Before the coming of Chriſt, there ſhall falſe Prophets ariſe, and ſay, I am Chriſt, and another I am Chriſt; that is paſt. Before the perſonall coming of Chriſt, there ſhall be warres and rumours of warres; this is paſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:162407:15"/>And before that day, there ſhall be great diviſions, even in the matter of Religion; one ſaying, Loe here is Chriſt, and another, Loe there is Chriſt; this is already. And imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before, and at his coming, men ſhall be ſmiting their fellow ſervants, eating and drinking with the drunken; this is already. The wiſe and the fooliſh Virgins, ſhall be all aſleepe; and was there ever a time, when both wiſe and fooliſh were more aſleepe then now? when men ſet themſelves to ſleepe, they draw their curtaines, put out their lights, and will have no more light come in; ſo now. When men are aſleepe, their ſenſes are bound up that were open before, they ſee not, heare not, taſte not, ſmell not; their ſenſes are lock't up. Sleep is, <hi>Ligatio ſenſuum.</hi> And was there ever time when mens ſenſes were more bound up, that were formerly exerciſed, then now? are there not ſome that would pray, and heare, and reade, that will not now? who have now throwne off all duties, ordinances, and meanes? Oh! what ſleeping is here? was there ever ſuch ſleeping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong profeſſors as now there is? if ever wiſe and fooliſh virgins were afleepe, they ſeeme to be in our dayes; and ſhall we ſleep alſo? will ye not rather watch and pray? watch and pray, pray and watch; and what I ſay to one, I ſay to all, <hi>watch and pray, leaſt ye enter into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take but two or three wakening obſervations from this Parable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If ye looke into this parable, ye may obſerve a moſt deſperate ſleepe is to come upon all proſeſſors, immediately before the coming, the great coming of Chriſt. I call that deſperate ſleepe, which is univerſall; this Parable fals upon the Churches; <hi>Then ſhall the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> (not the Kingdome of the world) <hi>be like to ten Virgins;</hi> and thoſe ten ſhall be all aſleepe, good and bad. And ſayes our Saviour in another place, <hi>Nevertheleſſe, when the ſon of man comes, ſhall he find Faith on earth?</hi> Againe, I call that a deſperate ſleepe, which ſhall be in the face of light. Its an hard thing to ſleepe, whilſt a candle is held unto ones
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:162407:15"/>eyes; and in the time before Chriſt comes, much light and truth ſhall breake out, as Antichriſtian errour goes off; and yet, even then, good and bad ſhall fall aſleepe.</p>
            <p>I call that deſperate, (againe) which ſhall be in the midſt of trouble. Its an hard thing for a man to ſleepe when he is pincht and ſtricken; in the times before Chriſt and when he comes, men ſhall be ſmiting their fellow ſervants; and yet, even the ſmitten ſhall be aſleepe. Oh! what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate ſleeping times ſhall the latter times be! have we not all cauſe then for to watch and pray?</p>
            <p>Againe ſecondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If ye looke into this Scripture or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ye find that thoſe who fall aſleepe immediately before the coming of Chriſt, ſhall never wake again till Chriſt come. And they all ſlept (ſayes the text of the ten Virgins) and waked not till the Bridegroome came.</p>
            <p>Now if a man be very ſleepy, and you come to him, and ſay, Sir, take heed of ſleeping, for if you do fall aſleepe, you will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wake again, will he not take heed of ſleeping? thus it ſhall be with the ſleepers of this latter time; at other times men ſhall ſleepe and wake, and wake and ſleepe; but if men fall aſſeepe, into a ſpirituall ſleepe immediately before the coming of Jeſus Chriſt, they ſhall ſleepe till he comes, and ſhall be wake't no more but by his coming: Oh! Lord, who would not watch and pray, leaſt he enter into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If ye obſerve this Parable, ye ſhall finde, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that there are two ſorts of ſleepers, and accordingly two events of their ſleeping.</p>
            <p>Some ſlept (as the wiſe Virgins) but did keep their oyle, their oyle not ſpent; theſe when the Bridegroome came, entred with him into his joy.</p>
            <p>Others there are that ſleepe, and have ſpent their oyle; had oyle, but ſpent it: and theſe when the Bridegroome cometh, are ſhut out; and though they call, Lord open; He anſwers, <hi>I know ye not.</hi> So now in the latter dayes, there ſhall be two ſorts of profeſſors, one that ſhall ſleepe and ſlumber, but they ſhall keepe their graces, their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:162407:16"/>oyle, their principles; and theſe, though they be found aſleepe when Chriſt comes, Chriſt will pardon, and their ſleeping, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſethey have ſtill their oyle.</p>
            <p>Others there ſhall be, who ſhall not only fall aſleepe, but they ſhall loſe their principles: True, I thought indeed, that a man was bound for to keep the ſabbath, to live ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to make a conſcience of every word and thought; but now I ſee there is more liberty; thus they ſhall loſe their principles, their oyle, their judgements: theſe poore ſoules ſhall never wake againe; and when Chriſt comes, though they cry to him for mercy, they will not obtaine it: No, ye have loſt your principles, your oyle, your judgements; ye are fooliſh Virgins, ye ſhall never enter into my joy, he will then ſay. Who would not then watch and pray? what I ſay to you, I ſpeak unto my own ſoule, and to every perſon here preſent, Oh! let us all watch; for the Son of man comes, and he comes at midnight; and if it be not midnight now, yet it is late already.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing all theſe things are ſo, give me leave Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Beloved, to leave an exhortation with you, which is no other, then that which the Pſalmiſt preſents unto ye in the 24. Pſalme. <hi>Lift up your heads O ye gates, and be lift up ye everlaſting doores, and the King of glory ſhall come in.</hi> Gates (ye know) are the place where the Magiſtrate fate: The Temple doore was called the Everlaſting doore; in oppoſition to the doore of the Tabernacle which was to continue but a little time: The Pſalmiſt ſpeakes here of Chriſts Kingdome and Lordſhip on earth, verſe 1. <hi>The earth is the Lords, and the fulneſſe thereof, the world and they that dwell therein.</hi> Then he will have a Church and a precious people: <hi>Who ſhall aſcend unto the hill of the Lord? who ſhall ſtand on his holy place?</hi> verſe the 3. Which he anſwers in the generall: <hi>He that hath cleane hands and a pure heart.</hi> And more particularly at the 6. verſe, <hi>This is the Generation of them that ſeeke him, that ſeeke thy face, even</hi> Jacob.</p>
            <p>The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had two names; ſometimes they were called <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they were in a more flouriſhing and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:162407:16"/>ſtrong condition: ſometimes they were in a low and weake condition, and then they were called <hi>Jacob; Feare not O worme</hi> Jacob. Now ſayes the Pſalmiſt here, <hi>The earth is the Lords, and Chriſt ſhall raigne, and the poore deſpiſed</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael, <hi>who now are in low condition, and therefore called</hi> Jacob, <hi>ſhall be converted, and aſcend unto the hill of God.</hi> Now therefore my advice and counſell unto you, is, That as the Lord Jeſus ſhall make any approach unto your Townes, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Kingdomes, Churches, you would receive him, and not ſhut your gates and doores againſt him: but O all ye Cities, Townes and Magiſtrates, lift up your heads, lift up your heads O ye gates, and all you Temple-men, and Churches, lift up your everlaſting doores, that this King of glory may come in. And if ye aske who it is? <hi>It is the Lord ſtrong and mighty, the Lord mighty in battel;</hi> wherefore <hi>lift up your heads.</hi> And becauſe this exhortation is of great conſequence, and men are ſlow to receive it, I exhort you to it againe, at the 9. verſe. <hi>Lift up your heads O ye gates, even lift them up ye everlaſting doores, and the King of glory ſhall come in.</hi> Now the Lord grant, that we may all ſo lift up our heads and gates, that this King of glory may come in among us, not as a judge to condemne us, but as our Bridegroome to love us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
